export const HISTORYA2014 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. The spread of Islam in West Africa in the 19th century was through",
A: "Jihads",
B: "Education",
C: "Fervent prayers",
D: "Pious life style",
answer: "A. Jihads",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. The European nation which came last in the acquisition of territories in Africa was",
A: "Portugal",
B: "Belgium",
C: "Germany",
D: "Britain",
answer: "C. Germany",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. The British explorers studied the socio-political and economic conditions of West African states to",
A: "enable Africans to set up industries",
B: "enable them to establish trading stations",
C: "make them more friendly with the Africans",
D: "make the African rulers more submissive",
answer: "B. enable them to establish trading stations",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The West African territory was called the ”white man’s grave” because",
A: "White men dug their own grave there",
B: "Of the harsh climatic and diseases",
C: "Graves of white men were many there",
D: "African rulers killed many white men",
answer: "B. Of the harsh climatic and diseases",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The trans-Atlantic slave trade in West Africa was started by the",
A: "French",
B: "Germany",
C: "Portuguese",
D: "Americans",
answer: "C. Portuguese",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Which of the following statement is true about the suppression of the trans-Atlantic Slave trade?",
A: "The works of literature changed people’s attitude to it",
B: "Suppression was made through payment of compensation",
C: "Slave trading was not profitable hence it was denounced",
D: "The industrial revolution promoted the trade",
answer: "B. Suppression was made through payment of compensation (This is incorrect. Suppression involved international treaties, naval blockades, and changing economic incentives.)",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. The country that led the abolition of the trans-Atlantic slave trade was",
A: "Germany",
B: "Portugal",
C: "France",
D: "Britain",
answer: "D. Britain",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. The most adverse effect of the trans-Atlantic slave trade was that",
A: "Africa was depopulated",
B: "All Africans did not benefit from the trade",
C: "Industrial vocation spread to all parts of Africa",
D: "Agriculture was promoted",
answer: "A. Africa was depopulated",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Which of the following contributed to the suppression of trans-Atlantic slave trade",
A: "Agrarian Revolution",
B: "Evangelical movement",
C: "Assiento agreement",
D: "Treaty of Berlin",
answer: "B. Evangelical movement",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. The purpose of establishing the American Colonization Society in 1816 was to",
A: "recruit American youth for evangelical mission",
B: "investigate how slaves were treated",
C: "determine where to settle the freed slaves from America",
D: "encourage the establishment of schools",
answer: "C. determine where to settle the freed slaves from America",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Which of the following countries was chosen by Britain as resettlement centre for the freed slave?",
A: "Sierra Leone",
B: "Liberia",
C: "The Gambia",
D: "Ghana",
answer: "B. Liberia",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. In order to encourage Christian converts to read the Bible, the missionaries",
A: "Studied local languages",
B: "Distributed Christian pamphlets",
C: "Preached the gospel to all nations",
D: "Gave the Holy Communion",
answer: "A. Studied local languages",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. All the following were reasons for missionary activities in West Africa except",
A: "To stop the slave trade",
B: "Promotion of legitimate trade",
C: "Establishment of industries",
D: "The spread of Christianity",
answer: "C. Establishment of industries",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The early missionaries believe that Africans would stop the slave trade once the",
A: "The traditional rulers became educated",
B: "Traditional rulers adopted European culture",
C: "Africans were made to renounce their gods",
D: "Africans were encouraged to accept Christianity",
answer: "C. Africans were made to renounce their gods",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Which among the following countries was the seat of Christian missionary activities in West Africa?",
A: "Sierra Leone",
B: "Liberia",
C: "Ghana",
D: "The Gambia",
answer: "A. Sierra Leone",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. The first Christian mission that came to West Africa in the 19th century belonged to",
A: "Church Missionary Society",
B: "Roman Catholic Mission",
C: "Wesleyan Mission Society",
D: "Church of Scotland Mission",
answer: "A. Church Missionary Society",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. The first African Bishop of the Church Missionary Society in West Africa was",
A: "Mensah Sarbah",
B: "Ajayi Crowther",
C: "Eddie Monoh",
D: "Olauda Equiano",
answer: "B. Ajayi Crowther",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. The drastic change in the system of production from hand to machine made products in Europe was referred to as",
A: "Scramble and petition",
B: "Colonial subjugation",
C: "Legitimate trade",
D: "Industrial revolution",
answer: "D. Industrial revolution",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The scramble for West African territories was more pronounced between",
A: "Holland and Britain",
B: "France and Germany",
C: "Holland and Germany",
D: "Britain and France",
answer: "B. France and Germany",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The policy of effective occupation agreed upon at the Berlin conference means that",
A: "A form of government must be established in the area of occupation",
B: "The European nation occupying any area must obtain permission from Germany",
C: "The government must train soldiers who would guard the area",
D: "African chiefs must be given powerful positions in government",
answer: "A. A form of government must be established in the area of occupation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. The Berlin conference of I 884-1885 was called at the instance of",
A: "Ottovon Bismark",
B: "Napoleon Bonaparte",
C: "King Leopold Il",
D: "Winston Churchill",
answer: "A. Ottovon Bismark",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. Apart from their imperial ambitions, the French in West Africa considered themselves as",
A: "Agents of civilization",
B: "Industrialists",
C: "Christian missionaries",
D: "The rulers’ equal",
answer: "A. Agents of civilization",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. In the French colonies, educated African were referred to as",
A: "Mulattoes",
B: "Originaries",
C: "Evolues",
D: "Sujets",
answer: "C. Evolues",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The British were able to expand their colonies in West Africa mainly through the",
A: "Signing of treaties",
B: "Use of the naval squadron",
C: "Activities of explorers",
D: "Activities of Krio merchant",
answer: "A. Signing of treaties",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. There were no major settler colonies in West Africa because",
A: "Europe was too far from West Africa",
B: "the traditional rulers killed the initial settlers",
C: "there was scarcity of land for settlement",
D: "of harsh climatic conditions in West Africa",
answer: "D. of harsh climatic conditions in West Africa",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. The nature and structure of colonial administration in West Africa aimed at",
A: "Industrializing the content",
B: "Deriving economic and political benefits",
C: "There was scarcity of land for settlement",
D: "Preserving the people’s culture",
answer: "B. Deriving economic and political benefits",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. The most important reason for the European colonization of Africa was",
A: "Economic exploitation",
B: "Extension of political influence",
C: "Introduction of Western civilization",
D: "Suppression of the slave trade",
answer: "A. Economic exploitation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The African rulers were defeated by European invaders because they",
A: "had larger armies",
B: "used superior weapons",
C: "had the American support",
D: "adopted guerilla warfare",
answer: "B. used superior weapons",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. The European faced opposition to their rule in West Africa because they",
A: "Were friendly with the elite",
B: "Did not give certificate to warrant chiefs",
C: "Denied the chiefs their entitlements",
D: "Disregarded traditional system of government",
answer: "D. Disregarded traditional system of government",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. One characteristic of Indirect rule was that it",
A: "Incorporated assimilated people",
B: "Emphasized the legitimacy of traditional rulers",
C: "Maintain the positions of their rulers",
D: "Regarded colonies as overseas department",
answer: "B. Emphasized the legitimacy of traditional rulers",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Africans fought several wars against the European powers in order to",
A: "Show their military tactics to the world",
B: "Prevent their territories from being colonized",
C: "Maintain the positions of their rulers",
D: "Expose educated Africans in colonial government",
answer: "B. Prevent their territories from being colonized",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Which of the following African countries was not a former British colony?",
A: "Ghana",
B: "Liberia",
C: "Nigeria",
D: "The Gambia",
answer: "B. Liberia",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Colonial economy in West Africa could be described as dependent because",
A: "Food crops were brought from Europe",
B: "It was based on mechanized farming",
C: "West Africans were not educated to plant food crops",
D: "It mainly produced raw materials for European industries",
answer: "D. It mainly produced raw materials for European industries",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Colonial economic policy which led to discontent among West Africans was",
A: "Exploitation of resources",
B: "Building of roads and railways",
C: "Payment of wages",
D: "Introduction of new crops",
answer: "A. Exploitation of resources",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. The colonial masters were reluctant to leave Africa because",
A: "They were encouraged by West Africans to stay",
B: "They did not wish the economic exploitation to end",
C: "West African climate was much better than theirs",
D: "They lacked the finance to leave",
answer: "B. They did not wish the economic exploitation to end",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. The transport development in West Africa by the colonial powers was to",
A: "Hasten the spread of indigenous technology",
B: "Foster quick movement of agricultural products overseas",
C: "Help West African countries to be self-sufficient",
D: "Hasten even development in West African countries",
answer: "B. Foster quick movement of agricultural products overseas",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Which of the following strategies was not adopted for consolidation of European culture in West Africa?",
A: "Cancellation of additional religion",
B: "Adoption of European languages",
C: "Adoption of European mode of dressing",
D: "Establishment of Western education",
answer: "A. Cancellation of additional religion (This is not a realistic or common method of cultural imposition.)",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Europeans were able to consolidate their culture in West Africa mainly because they",
A: "Encouraged production of cash crops",
B: "Promoted Western education",
C: "Resettled the ex-slaves in their environment",
D: "Encouraged nationalist struggles",
answer: "B. Promoted Western education",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. After the Second World War, the mandated territories were renamed",
A: "The Dominion",
B: "Trust territories",
C: "Green Belt Zone",
D: "Liberated territories",
answer: "B. Trust territories",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. African soldiers served during the First World War as",
A: "Commanders of European troops",
B: "Sailors in the British navy",
C: "Porters’ corps for the troops",
D: "Assistants to the medical corps",
answer: "C. Porters’ corps for the troops",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. A major reason for the success of the military administration in West African politics was",
A: "Quick decisions on matters",
B: "Abuse of human rights",
C: "Lack of freedom of the press",
D: "Disregard for democracy",
answer: "A. Quick decisions on matters",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. One problem of a military government is that it gives the members of the armed forces",
A: "A sense of superiority over others",
B: "Arms with which to kill people",
C: "Absolute freedom",
D: "More money than others",
answer: "A. A sense of superiority over others",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Dictatorial tendencies in the military emanated from possession from",
A: "Possession of guns",
B: "Fear of the civilians",
C: "The support received from the masses",
D: "Illiteracy among the masses",
answer: "A. Possession of guns",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. All the following were the expectation of African leaders at independence except the",
A: "need for more educational institutions",
B: "desire for socio-economic development",
C: "need to send African soldiers to Europe",
D: "desire to establish indigenous banks",
answer: "C. need to send African soldiers to Europe",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Which of the following statement best describe neo-colonialism? A process by which",
A: "Former colonial masters build industries in the independent African countries",
B: "Independent African countries seek military aid from their former colonial masters",
C: "Western powers continued to interfere in the affairs of African countries",
D: "Western powers offered scholarships to deserving African students",
answer: "C. Western powers continued to interfere in the affairs of African countries",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. A major reason for the under-development of West African states is",
A: "Bad governance",
B: "Negligence of duties",
C: "Family disputes",
D: "Absence of price control",
answer: "A. Bad governance",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. The most important cause of poverty in post-independent Africa is",
A: "Inadequate natural resources",
B: "Inadequate skilled manpower",
C: "Inadequate health facilities",
D: "Ineffective political leadership",
answer: "D. Ineffective political leadership",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. All the following are problems of West African states except",
A: "Influence of pressure groups",
B: "Widespread corruption",
C: "Promotion of egalitarian societies",
D: "Bad leadership",
answer: "C. Promotion of egalitarian societies",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. All the following factors sustained neo-colonialism except",
A: "Modern political systems",
B: "Language of ex-colonial powers",
C: "Establishment of Western education",
D: "Promotion of indigenous industries",
answer: "D. Promotion of indigenous industries",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. Which of the following is not a reason for boundary disputes in Africa?",
A: "Boundaries are artificial",
B: "Boundaries cut across ethnic groups",
C: "States belonged to different colonial masters",
D: "Roads were built by their colonial masters",
answer: "A. Boundaries are artificial",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]